Finding Aid for [University of Michigan dance card collection], 1888-1957
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
[University of Michigan dance card collection] 1888-1957
[University of Michigan dance card collection]
0.4 linear ft. (ca. 41 dance cards)
0576 Bimu 2
Dance cards from various University of Michigan dances and social events, including the J-Hop, Freshman Frolic, and Michigan Union Formal.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by a variety of individuals
Periodic additions to the collection expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
As various University of Michigan historians have noted, dances and formals have long been an important tradition at the University of Michigan. One of the most well-known dances at UM was the Junior Hop (or J-Hop). Modeled after the Senior Hop (which ran from 1868 to 1870), the first J-Hop was held in 1872 and became one of the most popular social events on campus (Wahr,The University of Michigan an encylopedic survey ). The J-Hop ended in 1960 "after which it was given up for lack of interest by a generation that preferred to sit and listen to folk music" (Peckham, The Making of the University of Michigan, 1967, p.76).
Students attended other dances as well at the University of Michigan, according to Peckham: "Big class dances, besides the venerable J Hop, were the Freshman Frolic, the Sophomore Prom, the Senior Reception, the Military Ball, and the Architects' Ball--all part of the rites of spring" (Peckham, p.151).
Dance cards were an integral part of the dance tradition in the United States as well as at the University of Michigan during the time of the J-Hop and other dance events. Dance cards were small cards or booklets distributed to women attending dances for the purpose of tracking their prospective dance partners; the dance cards also served as souvenirs of the event as well. Typically, a dance card would include a list of the evening's songs with an associated line on which a dance partner's name could be written for that dance. Dance cards ranged from the very simple to the elaborate and often included a cord with a tiny pencil attached. (dance card information from: http://www.mixedpickles.org/dancecards.html)
This collection includes dance cards from 1888 to 1947 from various University of Michigan dances and social events. The bulk of the dance cards are from the J-Hop, including different dance cards from the same year. The collection also includes dance cards from both the Michigan Union formal and the Frosh Frolic. The dance cards have been organized by the event and date. In this finding aid, the date refers to the date the dance was held, not the class year of those attending the dance. Other dance cards can be found in various scrapbook collections at the Bentley.
Subjects:
Michigan Union.; University of Michigan. Frosh Frolic.; University of Michigan. Junior Hop.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.
Genre Terms:
Dance cards.
- Frosh Frolic
  - Frosh Frolic, 1919 (Box 1)
  - Frosh Frolic, 1933 (Box 1)
- J-Hop
  - 1888 (Box 1)
  - 1889 (Box 1)
  - 1890 (Box 1)
  - 1893 (Box 1)
  - 1894 (Box 1)
  - 1901 (Box 1)
  - 1902 (Box 1)
  - 1903 (Box 1)
  - 1904 (Box 1)
  - [1905], 2 items (Box 1)
  - 1906, 2 items (Box 1)
  - 1907 (Box 1)
  - [1908] (Box 1)
  - [1909], 2 items (Box 1)
  - 1911, 2 items (Box 1)
  - 1912, 2 items (Box 1)
  - 1919 (Box 1)
  - [1919 ?] leather case (Box 1)
    (nothing inside)
  - 1920, 3 items (Box 1)
  - 1926 (Box 1)
  - 1934 (Box 1)
  - 1938 (Box 1)
  - 1947 (Box 1)
  - 1957 (Box 1)
- Michigan Union Formal
  - 1933 (Box 1)
  - 1934 (Box 1)
  - 1935 (Box 1)
  - 1936 (Box 1)
- Other
  - Freshman Spread, 1914 (Box 1)
  - M-Hop, 1943 (Box 1)
  - The Owl Girls' Ball, 1888 (Box 1)
  - Slide Rule Dance, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Sophomore Prom, 1934 (Box 1)
  - [event unknown], 1913 (Box 1)
  - [event unknown], 1915 (Box 1)